Good morning. All right, so today's דף daf is דף ט, daf
tes, nine, and we are dealing with the משנה mishna that in
addition to forbidding things that are labor-intensive,
which the גמרא Gemara has labeled טירחא, tircha, working the land, and
then things that are אבלות avelut related,
re-burying of the bones and getting worked up over הספדים hespeidim and
so on,
the משנה mishna then turned to things that you can't do because
they're שמחה simcha related, particularly getting married. And the reason the גמרא
Gemara gives is actually three or if you want four reasons. One
is the one that everyone knows, אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה. ein me'arvin
simcha b'simcha. Then there's a slightly more narrow aspect of that, which
is ושמחת בחגך, v'samachta b'chagecha, בחגך ולא באשתך. b'chagecha v'lo b'ishtecha. And
it's more narrow that number one, maybe just refers to specifically the
conflict of marriage and רגל. regel. Maybe if either one of those
two components is different, it would not be a problem. And also
the way that the גמרא Gemara frames it is specifically a concern
about abandoning שמחת הרגל simchas haregel for the sake of the שמחה
simcha of marriage. Whereas אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה ein me'arvin simcha b'simcha
is really, it could be a statement that you're not privileging one
over the other, you're just not able to give your full attention,
the attention that each one deserves on its own. The relevance of
the question of these two issues comes up with תוספות's Tosafot question
about a סעודת ברית מילה seudat bris milah or סעודת פדיון הבן
seudat pidyon haben and how that's not a problem. And תוספות Tosafot
answers well maybe the פדיון הבן pidyon haben you really can't postpone,
I mean you can postpone, you can't postpone the ברית, bris, so
therefore you really can't postpone the סעודה. seudah. I mean the ברית
מילה, bris milah, did I say ברית, bris, ברית מילה bris milah
you can't postpone the ברית bris so you can't really maybe reasonably
postpone the סעודה. seudah. פדיון הבן pidyon haben less clear and one
of תוספות's Tosafot answer is that maybe we don't rule the broader
אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה, ein me'arvin simcha b'simcha, maybe we only rule
the very narrow ושמחת בחגך ולא באשתך. v'samachta b'chagecha v'lo b'ishtecha.
The other answer of course is that not everything gets to a
level of שמחה simcha that creates this problem, it only has to
be high degrees of שמחה. simcha. But it is worth noting that
these two reasons are not the same,
and although we tend to quote the more generic one. And then
there are two other reasons which don't seem to fit in the
משנה mishna much at all, I mean in the פשט pshat of
the משנה, mishna, one is the amount of effort a wedding requires
and the other is a concern that people will postpone the wedding.
And then the גמרא Gemara asks certain questions about that. So now
we pick up five or six lines from the top on דף
ט עמוד א, daf tet amud aleph, one two three four five
six, six lines from the top and where the גמרא Gemara focuses
on אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה ein me'arvin simcha b'simcha which explains why
we tend to think that that is the primary principle. So let's
take a look. So it says, ודאין מערבין שמחה בשמחה מנלן? v'de'ein
me'arvin simcha b'simcha minalan? Where do we get this idea that you
do not mix up
שמחה בשמחה? simcha b'simcha? So גמרא Gemara says דכתיב ויעש שלמה בעת
ההיא את החג, dachtiv vaya'as shlomo ba'eis ha'hee es hachag, Shlomo made
at that time the festival, meaning סוכות, Sukkot, this is when he
was
dedicating the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, dedicating it, וכל ישראל עמו קהל
גדול מלבוא חמת עד נחל מצרים, v'chol yisrael imo kahal gadol mibo
chamas ad nachal mitzrayim, all of the Jewish people with him, you
know the an enormous congregation from מלבוא חמת עד נחל מצרים, mibo
chamas ad nachal mitzrayim, לפני ה׳ אלקינו שבעת
ימים ושבעת ימים ארבעה עשר יום, lifnei Hashem Elokeinu shivas yamim v'shivas
yamim arba'ah asar yom, before Hashem our G-d seven
days and seven days, fourteen days. So the גמרא Gemara says so
understands that it means seven days for חנוכת הבית chanukas habayis and
seven days for סוכות. Sukkot. So the גמרא Gemara asks an obvious
question, דאי סלקא דעתך דמערבין שמחה בשמחה, di mi'sei d'me'arvin simcha b'simcha,
if there would not have been a problem of mixing
שמחה בשמחה, simcha b'simcha, איבעי ליה למעבד חד חג, iba'i lei limvad
chad chag, why did he make everybody with then a whole huge
fourteen day commitment to this whole thing? Just, you know, double it
up. Have the סוכות Sukkot be seven days of סוכות Sukkot and
seven days of חנוכת הבית. chanukas habayis. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, ודילמא מינטרא לא נטרינן, v'dilma minteira lo natrinan, והיכא דאיתרמיאן
עבדינן, v'heicha d'isreimyan abdinan, one minute the גמרא Gemara says. It just
so happened that they finished up everything a week before סוכות. Sukkot.
So okay they're not going to postpone the dedication ceremony דווקא davka
to make it overlap with סוכות. Sukkot. I get that you don't
want
to proactively try to overlap them, but if it would happen to
be that this would be the time that would make sense there's
no proof that you would
not schedule it if it happened to fall out on סוכות. Sukkot.
So the most you can learn from that is is that you
know is that you take you know is that you don't, it
would be inappropriate to proactively try to get them together. But that
doesn't mean you have to work to separate them.
So the גמרא Gemara says, איבעי ליה לשירויי פורתא. iba'i lei l'shiruya
pursa. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. You know the גמרא Gemara says
if you're telling me that if it would fall out then we
would do it, the גמרא Gemara says like who really gets to
decide when things are done, right? Okay the construction is
done, we're
now... What made you have to finish a week before? Sort of
left over a tiny little section that you had not finished and
you leave the last finishing for סוכות Sukkot and you make it
happen, like you do for סיום Siyum exactly. So the point is,
is that if there really wouldn't have been a problem of having
them at the same time, it could have fallen out that they
were at the same time. It seems like they had to make
sure that didn't happen.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, שיורי בנין בית המקדש לא משיירינן.
shiurei binyan Beit HaMikdash lo mash'arinan. No, no, no, no, no. We
can't. If you're dealing with other things, maybe. If you're dealing with
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, there's no way you can sort of
schlep it out and leave something in order to make it happen,
in order to make it happen at the right time. That wouldn't
be appropriate to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. When it's done, it's
done, and then you have to have your שמחה. simcha. And so
that doesn't... so therefore there's no proof from there because okay, they
didn't postpone the שמחה, simcha, but that's because they finished early. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, איבעי ליה לשיורי דאמה כליא עורב.
ibai lei lishiyurei d'ama kalya orev. You still could have left something
over that would not have been seen as really leaving over and
would have allowed these to happen at the same time. What could
you have left over? The אמה, ama, which is like a post
the size of an
אמה, ama, of an arm's length, and they
basically at the roof of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I'm going
to draw a picture for you here.
At the roof here, I mean if this is whatever, this courtyard
or whatever. I mean this is the courtyard and there's... This is
what a teacher in גמרא Gemara classes, drawing 101.
Anyway, so they would have, right? They'd... they would have a big
type of a post, pointy post here. Okay, and what the purpose...
or maybe there would be, I don't know, maybe there would be
a lot of spikes.
Spikes, yeah, I
don't know, anyway, whatever it would be, it'd be an אמה ama
wide. It was so that the ravens don't come and perch here,
waiting to fly down and eat from the food of the קרבנות,
korbanot, okay? So they would have these spikes called אמה כליא עורב,
ama kalya orev, right? The אמה ama that sort of gets rid
of the ravens, at the top of the... at the top. Didn't
they move one אמה?
ama? I mean it goes the whole strip.
Yeah, I don't know, there might have been a lot of them.
Like all over New York City. You see them all over New
York on roofs, they have like these little spiky things. Spiky things,
yeah. So the pigeons...
Okay,
so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara assumes that that's not part of
the בנין binyan per se, that's an addition to it and therefore
it would have been acceptable to have postponed with that. So the
גמרא Gemara and therefore again, the fact that they did
not... logically it would have made sense... no, but you still have
a reason not to have... if it would not have been a
problem to have it at the same time, they could have arranged
it the same time. The fact they didn't shows that it would
have been a problem. They could have arranged it by waiting to
finish this אמה. ama. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אמה כליא עורב צריך בנין הבית. ama kalya
orev tzarich binyan habayit. No, that's still related to the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, even if it's not part of the central structure itself.
So, alright, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says you can't prove from
the fact they didn't happen at the same time that they're not
allowed to happen at the same time. Happened that they finished early,
okay? And for various reasons they couldn't have arranged it to finish
later. Alright, and therefore that's why, so they won't actively postpone it
from when it's supposed to happen, but that doesn't prove you have
to make them not happen at the same time. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא מדאיתר קרא, ella mideiyatar kra, fine. From the event
that it happened early you can't prove anything. But from the language
of the verse you can prove that that's what was going on.
Why? מכדי, machtei, let's take a look. כתיב ארבעה עשר יום, kativ
arba'ah asar yom, 14 days. שבעת ימים ושבעת ימים למה לי? shivat
yamim v'shivat yamim lamma li? Why did it have to spell out
seven days and seven days? Say 14 days, obviously I would have
understood. Now, so שמע מינה הני לחווד והני לחווד. shma mina hani
l'chud v'hani l'chud. It shows you that each one was intentionally kept
distinct. The seven days of the חנוכת הבית chanukat habayit was intentionally
kept distinct from the seven days of סוכות. Sukkot. Maybe the פסוק
pasuk just wants us to know how many days of חנוכת הבית,
chanukat habayit, how many days of סוכות. Sukkot. But anyway, the fact
that it goes out of its way to say seven and seven
is to show that these two must remain distinct. And this proves
right, אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה, ein marvin simcha b'simcha, because this has
nothing to do with getting married. It does have to do with
רגל, regel, but nothing to do with getting married. So you see
anyway that the גמרא Gemara is now working with this idea as
a broader principle. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר פרנך אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Parnach amar Rabbi Yochanan, says פרנך
Parnach in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אותה שנה לא
עשו ישראל את יום הכפורים. otah shana lo asu Yisrael et Yom
Kippurim. That year the Jewish people did not celebrate יום הכפורים. Yom
Kippurim. Why not? They didn't fast. Because seven days before סוכות Sukkot
gets into יום כפור, Yom Kippur, overlaps with יום כפור. Yom Kippur.
And if they're feasting, like it says that those were days of
feasting, so they didn't eat... they ate on יום כפור. Yom Kippur.
Okay, now, והיו דואגים, v'hayu do'agim, and
so they were worried, so לא עשו's lo asu an interesting phrase,
presumably they didn't. Presumably they did the קרבנות, korbonot, interesting question did
they
do the קרבנות korbonot during this period when it was being חנוכה
chanukka anyway, but they didn't eat, they ate on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Also interesting question פשטו עשו ישראל, pshatu asu yisrael, right? I
mean here it is true the פסוק pasuk says קהל גדול ככל
ישראל מלבוא חמת עד נחל מצרים, kahal gadol k'chol yisrael mi'lavo chamas
ad nachal mitzrayim, but you do imagine that the entire land didn't
empty of people and everybody comes to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? So I'm
sure there were people from all around the country. But okay, the
פסוק pasuk describes it as all of ישראל, Yisrael, right, כל ישראל,
kol yisrael, so we're going to describe it that way as well.
So the ישראל Yisrael did not observe יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. והיו
דואגים ואומרים ve-hayu do'agim ve-omrim and they were and they were, you
know, anxious or they were troubled and they said שמא נתחייבו שונאיהם
של ישראל כליה, shema nitchayvu soneihem shel yisrael kilaya, maybe the enemies
of ישראל, Yisrael, which is a euphemism, maybe we, the Jewish people,
are deserving of destruction, you know, of being wiped out, we violated
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's interesting, right, they felt that only after
the fact, they didn't hesitate beforehand, but okay, you know, the king
is telling you to do it, you feel compelled and everybody else
is doing it, you're looking around, everybody else is looking around at
everybody else and everybody is doing it, you feel compelled, but it
doesn't mean that they did not have a tremendous sense of, like,
guilt and worry over it. יצתה בת קול ואמרה, yatzta bas kol
ve-amra, a heavenly voice came out and said להם, lahem, כולם מזומנים
לחיי העולם הבא. kulam mezumanim le-chayei ha-olam ha-ba. No, you are all
designated for the world to come. So מאי דרש, mai darash, so
what allowed them to think or what allowed שלמה, Shlomo, whatever, to
think that you could eat on יום כיפור Yom Kippur if it's
part of the context of בנין הבית binyan ha-bayis of dedicating the
בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So אמרו, amru, they said, it's interesting אמרו,
amru, they said, like was it the people that decided this or
was it שלמה Shlomo that decided this? Anyway, קל וחומר, kal va-chomer,
let's make a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה משכן שאין קדושתו קדושת
עולם, u-mah mishkan she-ein kedushato kedushat olam, when it comes to dedicating
the משכן, mishkan, the משכן mishkan did not have eternal sanctity, right,
after it was going to be deconstructed and then they were going
to have put up the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So אירע וקרבן
יחיד דוחה שבת דאיסור סקילה eira ve-korban yachid docheh shabbos de-isur sekila
and when it was dedicated the נשיאים nesi'im brought קרבנות korbonos and
each those were private קרבנות korbonos of each נשיא, nasi, and it
overrode שבת. shabbos. How do you know it overrode שבת? shabbos? Because
the dedication of the משכן mishkan went for twelve days. So what
do we see? For the sake of dedicating the משכן mishkan which
has temporary sanctity, a personal קרבן korban could override שבת shabbos which
is very heavy, wait a minute. Okay, but anyway דוחה שבת דאיסור
סקילה, docheh shabbos de-isur sekila, מקדש שקדושתו קדושת עולם, mikdash she-kedushato kedushat
olam, so מקדש mikdash for the dedication of the מקדש mikdash which
is weightier than the משכן, mishkan, it's an eternal sanctity, וקרבן ציבור,
ve-korban tzibbur, and you've got a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, not just
the קרבן korban of the individual that is being brought, the individual
נשיאים. nesi'im. You have קרבנות korbonos of all, you know, when they
were bringing קרבנות korbonos when the פסוקים psukim describe the dedication of
the מקדש mikdash it describes all of the sacrifices they were bringing.
Those were being brought for behalf of the entire community, it wasn't
individuals bringing קרבנות. korbonos. All right, we're going to get to that.
ויום הכיפורים דענוש כרת ve-yom ha-kippurim de-anush kares and you have a
weaker thing that it has to override, it only has to override
יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, לא כל שכן, lo kol she-ken, how much
more so. So all three components of שלמה Shlomo was weightier, right?
It was for the sake of מקדש mikdash which has a weightier
קדושה, kedusha, the overriding thing was weightier, it was a קרבן ציבור
korban tzibbur not a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid, and the thing it
was overriding in the case of the מקדש mikdash was easier to
be overriden. It was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it wasn't שבת. shabbos.
So that's a great קל וחומר kal va-chomer and all three points
it scores. Except the little problem as Mike says, who says you're
allowed to eat? So bring the קרבנות, korbonos, okay, so let's take
a look.
Why is it easier to override יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Because it's only כרת kares and שבת shabbos is סקילה, sekila, so
that's a... okay. גמרא gemara says
אלא אמה היו דואגים? ela ama hayu do'agim? גמרא gemara says that's
such a good קל וחומר kal va-chomer why were they worried? So
the גמרא gemara says
התם צורך גבוה הכא צורך הדיוט. hasam tzorech gavo'ah hacha tzorech hedyot.
So the גמרא gemara says well there's still a difference, in the
case of the משכן mishkan they were bringing a קרבן korban to
God, here they were eating themselves, so that's what makes it a
little bit different. So the גמרא gemara says הכא נמי, hacha nami,
so the גמרא gemara says taka that's a good point, so what
made them feel they had to eat? הכא נמי מעבד לעבדי ומיכל
לא ניכל, hacha nami me'avad le'avdi u-meichal lo neichal, bring your קרבן
korban don't eat them. So the גמרא gemara says ולא לישתו, ve-lo
lishtu, don't drink. So the גמרא gemara says אין שמחה בלא אכילה
ושתיה, ein simcha belo achila u-shtiya, no, there was a feeling that
the dedication had to be אית שמחה is simcha and שמחה simcha
requires eating and drinking. So you would not be a proper dedication
of the מקדש, mikdash, it wasn't just hey as a side effect
we're eating. What are we talking about like a סעודת מצוה, se'udas
mitzvah, right? It doesn't mean like oh you know it's nice for
you to
eat... the fact that you do a סעודת מצוה se'udas mitzvah is
part of what makes it a שמחת מצוה. simchas mitzvah. Your eating,
it's not just your eating is nice it becomes religious because you
know it's being done for the sake of a מצוה. mitzvah. It's
also that your participating in the סעודה se'uda is part of what
creates the שמחה simcha and therefore that's why it's a מצוה. mitzvah.
So therefore, it's not like, "Oh, bring the קרבנות korbanos and don't
eat." No, if we had to make it a שמחה simcha for
the sake of the חנוכה, Chanukah, we had to eat in order
to create it as a reality of a שמחה. simcha. And therefore
they had to eat. It's interesting because normally we
said, normally people know by יום טוב, Yom Tov, אין שמחה אלא
בבשר ויין. ein simcha ela b'basar v'yayin. But really what the גמרא
Gemara says is אין שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים, ein simcha ela b'basar
shelamim, that you eat the קרבן korban and that's the real
שמחה. simcha. So here, normally, so that's talking about the קרבן korban
aspect, the bring of the שלמים, shelamim, but it's also the eating
of the קרבן שלמים. korban shelamim. You have the same thing here.
It's not enough to bring the קרבנות, korbanos, if you want to
create the שמחה, simcha, you have to actually be doing the eating
and the drinking. Okay. But nevertheless, so even though that clearly was
what you need to create the שמחה, simcha, they felt very worried,
because at the bottom line, when you're actually eating all those delicious
hors d'oeuvres, you can say as much as you want, it's all
a מצוה mitzvah and it's all for the שמחה simcha and so
on, and it really is, but to some degree you're also enjoying
it yourself and it's feeling like a more
not such a holy activity at times. So you worried, was this
really allowed on יום כפור? Yom Kippur?
Is it a קרבן חגיגה korban chagigah in addition to what the
גמרא Gemara is describing here or this is the חגיגה chagigah that
it's talking about?
The חגיגה chagigah was not on, wasn't on רגל. regal. They were
bringing שלמים. shelamim.
This was not סוכות. Sukkos.
It was the week before סוכות, Sukkos, yeah.
And then in spreading it out, wouldn't they obviously ate the whole
purpose? Meaning, like you just, they ate on צום גדליה. Tzom Gedaliah.
Yeah, yeah, that's not exactly שמחה.
simcha. Just putting it out, I just want to understand what the
גמרא Gemara says. Is it that they really did it distinct seven
days, even though it said they did the חג chag for fourteen
days, but it was really bifurcated? Seven days as for the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and another seven days for סוכות, Sukkos, which had
nothing to do with the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? Right, exactly.
Well, I don't know if it had nothing when they rededicated the
מקדש Mikdash in the time of חנוכה, Chanukah, they called it a
סוכות, Sukkos, in כסלו Kislev and the identification of סוכות Sukkos with
חנוכת הבית Chanukas HaBayis and so on, but
anyway, but it was did not overlap in terms of the exact
time.
And the thing they do then, it would be מרבה שמחה. marbeh
simcha. I understand.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says: אין שמחה בלא אכילה ושתיה. ein simcha belo achilah
ushtiah. ומשכן דחי שבת מנלן? v'mishkan dachi Shabbos minalan? How do you
know when they dedicated the משכן, Mishkan, they brought the קרבן korban
on שבת Shabbos of the נשיאים? nesi'im? אילמא מדכתיב ביום הראשון וביום
השביעי, ileima m'diksiv b'yom harishon u'vyom hashvii, on the first day this
נשיא nasi brought, second, third, fourth, seventh day. So if it's the
seventh day, presumably one of those days between one and seven falls
out on שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says: דילמא שביעי לקרבנות?
dilma shvii l'korbanos? No, maybe it means the first day of the
bringing. It doesn't mean you didn't skip over שבת. Shabbos. So day
seven, assuming the first bringing was on a Sunday, day seven doesn't
mean שבת, Shabbos, it means the seventh day of the bringing, we're
not counting שבת, Shabbos, שבת Shabbos there was no קרבנות. korbanos. So
how do you know that they
brought, how do you know the נשיאים nesi'im brought the קרבן korban
on שבת? Shabbos? Because it says this guy brought on day one,
this guy on day two, this guy on day three, so one
of them is bringing on שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says:
No, maybe it's day one, day two, day three of the days
of bringing, but it's not meaning that they're consecutive. אמר רב נחמן
בר
יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says: ביום עשתי עשר יום. b'yom ashti asar yom. It says the
word "day" twice. So why does it say the word "day" twice?
מה יום כולו רצוף אף עשתי עשר כולו רצופים. ma yom kulo
ratzuf af ashti asar kulo rutzufim. The same way a day is
continuous, there's no break up in the day, so therefore the eleven
were continuous, it was a straight eleven days, and therefore there was
no skipping over of שבת Shabbos in the middle. So the גמרא
Gemara says: דילמא ימים הראויים? dilma yamim haruyim? So the גמרא Gemara
still resists. No, maybe it means that on days that were fit
to bring קרבן, korban, there was no interruption, but it doesn't still
mean that every day was brought. כתיב קרא אחרינא, ksiv kra achina,
another verse says: ביום שנים עשר יום. b'yom shneim asar yom. It
repeats the word "day" again. On the day, the twelfth day. So,
מה יום כולו רצוף אף שנים עשר יום כולו רצופים. ma yom
kulo ratzuf af shneim asar yom kulo rutzufim. Fine, so that's how
we know that they brought on שבת. Shabbos. ודילמא, v'dilma, says the
גמרא, Gemara, הכא נמי ימים הראויים? hacha nami yamim haruyim? גמרא Gemara
says, wait a minute, how do you know here they brought on
יום כפור? Yom Kippur? Maybe it says they did it for seven
days, but seven days doesn't mean consecutive, maybe the seven days of
שלמה Shlomo was with a break for יום כפור? Yom Kippur? So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, אם כן תרי קראי למה לי? im
kein trei krai lama li?
Why do you need two פסוקים? psukim? Meaning why does it have
to say
ביום שנים עשר יום b'yom shneim asar yom and the eleventh day,
both trying to make the same point? And then the גמרא Gemara
is saying the twelfth day just like the eleventh...
oh, no, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. Right. ודילמא הכא נמי, v'dilma
hacha nami, we're not back to שלמה Shlomo yet. ודילמא הכא נמי,
v'dilma hacha nami, thank you, maybe here by the twelve days נמי
ימים הראויים? nami yamim haruyim? It means twelve days but with only
without interruptions on days you can bring, but there will be a
skip for שבת? Shabbos? No, אם כן תרי קראי למה לי? im
kein trei krai lama li? It wouldn't have to say both by
eleven and by twelve. If I say by eleven and by twelve,
it means no interruptions at all, even on שבת. Shabbos. Now the
גמרא Gemara gets to the שלמה Shlomo case. So that's how we
know about the נשיאים. nesi'im. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומקדש דחי
יום הכפורים מנלן? u'Mikdash dachi Yom HaKippurim minalan? How do you know
by the מקדש, Mikdash, they did it on יום כפור? Yom Kippur?
אילמא מדכתיב, ileima m'diksiv, if you say because it says... 14 days,
fourteen days, ודילמא ימים הראויים, v'dilma yamim ha-re'uyim,
same point, maybe it means fourteen, maybe these were days not including
you know, שבת Shabbos and יום כפור, Yom Kippur, or certainly not
including יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So how do you know it means
without interruption? So the גמרא Gemara says, גמר יום יום מהתם. gamar
yom yom me-hasam. No, the same way it says here שנים עשר
יום, shneim asar yom, and there it says ביום, be-yom, שנים עשר
יום, shneim asar yom, you know ביום השנים עשר, be-yom ha-shneim asar,
etc., so that tells you the same way in the original חנוכת
המשכן Chanukas Ha-Mishkan it was without interruption, in this חנוכת המקדש Chanukas
Ha-Mikdash there was also no interruption. So you know they did it
on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, יצתה בת קול ואמרה להם כולכם מזומנים לחיי
העולם הבא. yatzta bas kol v'amrah lahem kulchem mezumanim le-chayei ha-olam haba.
Now the second part. Now we figured out why they did it,
but we also figured out why they were so worried, and now
we get to the fact that they were reassured. This heavenly voice
came
out. ומנלן דאחל להו? u-minalan de-achal le-hu? How do we know the
heavenly voice came out? How do we know that they were forgiven?
דתני תחליפא, de-tani Tachlifa, because Tachlifa taught, ביום השמיני שלח את העם.
ba-yom ha-shmini shillach es ha-am. This is the end of that, on
the eighth day he sent the people
home. ויברכו את המלך, vayivarchu es ha-melech, and they blessed the king.
וילכו לאהליהם, vayelchu le-oholeihem, and they went to their tents, שמחים וטובי
לב, smeichim v'tuvei lev, happy and good of heart, על כל הטובה
אשר עשה ה' לדוד עבדו ולישראל עמו, al kol ha-tova asher asa
Hashem l'David avdo u-l'Yisrael ammo, for all the good that God did
to David His servant and to Israel His people. So what does
this mean? So let's break up the פסוק. pasuk. Let's look at
the components. לאהליהם, le-oholeihem, to their tents, שהלכו ומצאו נשותיהם בטהרה. she-halchu
u-matzu nesho-seihem be-taharah. So their tents means their homes means their wives,
because we're assuming basically that we're talking about the men. So therefore,
sort of like the whole הר סיני Har Sinai thing, שובו לכם
לאהליכם. shuvu lachem le-oholeichem. So therefore, their wives were טהורות, tehoros, they
weren't נדות, niddos, so they were able to go back and be
with their wives. They'd been away for fourteen days. שמחים, smeichim, שנהנו
מזיו שכינה, she-nehenu mi-ziv shechinah,
joyous because they had this like religious joy, they had basked in
the divine glow. וטובי לב, v'tuvei lev, and of
good heart, שכל
אחד ואחד נתעברה אשתו בבן זכר, she-kol echad v'echad nisabrah ishto be-ven
zachar, when they went home, everyone, everyone's wife after they were together
with their wives became pregnant with a male son, male דוקא. davka.
Okay, again the male emphasis. Okay, I don't know how he connects
that specifically to טובי לב. tuvei lev. Anyway, על כל הטובה, al
kol ha-tova,
so what's this again? After all of that, what's on all the
goodness? שיצתה בת קול ואמרה להם כולכם מזומנים לחיי העולם הבא. she-yatzta
bas kol v'amrah lahem kulchem mezumanim le-chayei ha-olam haba. You're all, you're
all designated for the world to come. So again, it's not exactly
clear how you get it from the פסוק. pasuk. It's how you
choose to read the various words of the פסוק. pasuk. But nevertheless,
the פסוקים psukim speak about all of this positive that resulted from
it, you know, and therefore clearly they could not have been
had the sin, the weight of the sin hanging over them if
this weren't true. Okay, כולכם מזומנים לחיי העולם הבא. kulchem mezumanim le-chayei
ha-olam haba. Now we have to finish interpreting the
פסוק. pasuk. לדוד עבדו, l'David avdo, David His servant, ולישראל עמו. u-l'Yisrael
ammo. בשלמא לישראל עמו, bishlama l'Yisrael ammo, I understand why God now
did good to Israel the people, דאחל להו עון יום הכפורים, de-achal
le-hu avon Yom HaKippurim, because He forgave the sin of יום כפור.
Yom Kippur. אלא לדוד עבדו מאי היא? ella l'David avdo mai hi?
What was the good that God did to David? Where would, I
mean know, Shlomo dedicated the מקדש, Mikdash, the people were, you know,
so what's the, now of course the funny point is that the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is the good is that He
allowed them the promise that He made to David, He allowed it
to finally culminate in the building of the מקדש, Mikdash, and the
good to the people is that the people now have a מקדש.
Mikdash. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara sort of wants to see that
it's referring to something else beyond just that. So for the people,
that they were forgiven, that they did not, you know, they weren't,
they did not have the burden of the sin hanging over them.
But how about, how about David? בשלמא לישראל עמו, bishlama l'Yisrael ammo,
that's that. מאי היא? mai hi? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב בשעה
שביקש שלמה להכניס ארון למקדש. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav be-sha'ah she-bikeish
Shlomo le-hachnis aron la-mikdash. When Shlomo wanted to finally bring in the
ארון aron into the sanctuary, into the sanctuary, דבקו שערים זה בזה.
davku she'arim zeh ba-zeh. The gates stuck to one another. And therefore
he couldn't get into the gates. אמר שלמה עשרים וארבע רננות ולא
נענה. amar Shlomo esrim v'arba'ah renanos v'lo ne'eneh. He said the twenty-four
רננות, renanos, right, because if you read the, you know, his prayer
when he dedicated the מקדש, Mikdash, he says people will turn, you
know, somebody will, people will turn to you with רנה, rinah, with
תפילה, tefillah, with בקשה. bakasha. He describes all the ways in which
people will pray to God via the מקדש Mikdash and he uses
all different terminologies of ways of words for prayer. Yes. So he
said all of that and the gates still stuck. Okay, so he's
trying to say, God, like, you know, I appreciate the power of
the מקדש Mikdash here, and maybe all those different words were also
his own sense of prayer, but it wasn't happening, God wasn't responding.
פתח ואמר, patach v'amar,
so then he opened up with a פסוק pasuk from תהלים, Tehillim,
שאו שערים ראשיכם והנשאו פתחי עולם ויבא מלך הכבוד. se'u she'arim rasheichem
v'hinas'u pischei olam v'yavo melech ha-kavod. So מי הוא זה מלך הכבוד?
mi hu zeh melech ha-kavod? So okay, not Shlomo, ה' הוא מלך
הכבוד. Hashem hu melech ha-kavod. So anyway, but God, we're bringing the
ארון aron in, you know, you're the King, the gates need to
open up, so you, the ארון, aron, God's, you know, presence, the
ארון aron can come into the מקדש. Mikdash. Very beautiful read of
the שאו שערים ראשיכם, Se'u Shearim Rasheichem, but you know what? גארנישט
העלפן. Gornisht helfen. So לא נענה, lo ne'ena, he was not answered.
כיון שאמר Kivan she'amar then
finally he said, now this is going to the תפילה tefillah he
said that's quoted דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, not מלכים א, Melachim Aleph,
השם אלקים אל תשב פני משיחך, Hashem Elokim al tashev penei meshichecha,
השם Hashem God do not turn back the face of your anointed
ones, זכרה לחסדי דויד עבדך, zachra l'chasdei David avdecha,
remember the good, the kindness of David your servant. Then when he
mentioned David, מיד נענה, miyad ne'ena, he was immediately answered. So that's
it, you see the good that God had done for it was
all for the sake of David, it was being very clear.
ואמר, v'amar, didn't he have that last part of it?
Right, that's the version of it in דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim. באותה
שעה, be'otah sha'ah, that moment, נהפכו פני שונאי דוד כשולי קדירה. nehepchu
penei sonei David k'shulei kederah. The face of those that hate David
turned like as dark as like the bottom of a pot. They
were like shamed. You see that all of this was for King
David. So וידעו
הכל v'yadu hakol
and everyone knew שמחל לו הקדוש ברוך הוא על אותו עוון, shemachal
lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu al oto avon, that God had forgiven him
for that sin, meaning the sin of בת שבע Bat Sheva and
אוריה Uriah and so on. So presumably that had always been like
hanging over him. So the same way the people got the sin
that was hanging over them erased about eating on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, it's clear that David had been atoned for. So here we
have in the context of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, being people atoned
for for their various sins, for the very sin of eating on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? I'm not saying that David was atoned
because of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but it's worth noting the juxtaposition
of those things, right? And therefore you see they knew that David
was forgiven because all of this was for the sake of King
David. Quite fascinating number one, right? The fact that חז"ל Chazal sort
of imagine two things. Number one, here it is, it's already the
period of שלמה, Shlomo, David is dead and buried and know the
way David is portrayed in תנ"ך, Tanach, he's an extremely popular king,
right? And imagine that he still has these like enemies that are
like you know even afterwards like have it in for King David
and are so sort of you know sort of shamed, you know
devastated when it shows that David has you know that you know
the glory of David, so just just you know shows you sort
of a reality. Right and the other thing, it's not exactly clear
that you know that why they were his enemies. Were they his
political enemies or so on, but by the juxtaposition also what it
frames is that that you know the their understanding that David had
not really been forgiven, you know or the people's understanding or חז"ל's
Chazal's understanding that the sin of בת שבע Bat Sheva and אוריה
Uriah did not go away so easily and it was only at
this much later time where there was sort of evidence you know
in terms of what that happened. And you see that elsewhere in
חז"ל, Chazal, this idea of both David's enemies and the sin of
אוריה Uriah ובת שבע. uBat Sheva. Like it has where a famous
מדרש, Midrash, I'm not remembering exactly but anyway where it sort of
has that you know King David is walking and some people say,
hey King David, what's the עונש onesh for somebody who sleeps with
a married woman? So he says, so the answer is he says
ית סקילה yat skilah but he gets עולם הבא, Olam Haba, but
somebody who is מביש פני חברו ברבים mevaysh pnei chavero berabbim doesn't
get עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So you know cute little exchange there.
But again you see this feeling that there are people that still
have it in for him דוקא davka because of the sin, not
for other sort of political or personal reasons. Anyway that's the story
here.
Okay so yes also the connection with בת שבע Bat Sheva and
שלמה Shlomo is that שלמה Shlomo then is built now that he's
king at this moment. Right.
Oh yeah that's a good point you know I mean it wasn't
the son that was that resulted you know during that initial sin
but right but it was right but it was from בת שבע,
Bat Sheva, that's true. So that's an excellent point as well but
דוקא davka it's
שלמה Shlomo the son of בת שבע, Bat Sheva, you know it
has a real power. Thank you for that, right. Okay so okay
רבי יונתן בן אסמיי ורבי יהודה בן גרים תנו פרשת נדרים בי
רבי שמעון בן יוחי. Rabbi Yonatan ben Asmai v'Rabbi Yehuda ben Gerim
tnu parshas nedarim bei Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. So this is not
going to seem seems like an aside but we'll see how it
ties in. So these two rabbis whose names we barely ever hear,
they were learning you know the מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim and you
know they were learning the משניות mishnayos etc. the word תנו tnu
like they were learning all of the tannaitic material in the house
of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, the ישיבה. yeshiva.
איפטור מיניה באורתא. Iptur minei be'orta. So they had spent a week
with him or however long they'd spent with him and then they
took their leave from him at night and they said goodbye and
they were planning the next day to head back to their
hometown. לצפרא, Letzafra, the next morning, הדרו וקמפטרי מיניה, hadru v'kamptari minei,
they went back to his house and said okay we're off goodbye.
So he said אמר להו amar lehu or he back מיפטרי מיניה
miftari minei means more than that it just means like we we
asked to take your leave you know it's so obviously it's a
show of respect and deference. So anyway so אמר להו amar lehu
he said to them ולא איפטריתו מינאי באורתא? v'la iptaritu minai be'orta?
I don't understand you took your leave from me last night why
are you coming back this morning to take your leave from me?
אמרו
ליה amru leh they said to him למדתנו רבנו limadtanu rabbeinu our
master taught us תלמיד שנפטר מרבו ולן באותה העיר talmid sheniftar me'rabo
velan be'otah ha'ir if a student takes leave of his master and
does not go home immediately but sleeps in that same city. that
night in the city, you know, you're gonna get started the next
day, you don't drive, you don't go in the night, especially in
those days, so צריך ליפטר ממנו פעם אחרת tzarich lipatar mimenu pa'am
acheret when you're getting up the next morning and you're really gonna
start on your journey, you have to go back and take a
leave again. Where do you know that? So שנאמר shenemar because we
see by שלמה, Shlomo, ביום השמיני שלח את העם ויברכו את המלך,
bayom hashemini shillach et ha'am vayevarchu et hamelech,
on the eighth day he sent the people and they blessed the
king, the eighth day counting from סוכות Sukkot is day 22, okay,
starts on the 15th, the eighth day is day 22. וכתיב uchitiv
and then the next verse says, וביום עשרים ושלושה לחודש השביעי שלח
את העם, uveyom esrim ushlosha lechodesh hashevii shillach et ha'am, on day
23 he sent the people out. So how could it be? It
already says that he sent them on day eight which was to
the 22nd of תשרי, Tishrei, and here it says they sent them
on the 23rd of
תשרי. Tishrei. So אלא מכאן לתלמיד הנפטר מרבו ולן באותה העיר צריך
ליפטר ממנו פעם אחרת. ella mikan letalmid haniftar merabbo velan be'oto ha'ir
tzarich lipatar mimenu pa'am acheret. All right, but you see that before
you take leave from somebody who's greater than you, you're right, changing
king and subject to student and רבי, Rebbe, that's true they do
that elsewhere, you have to take leave again the day that you're
leaving. Okay, so that's what they said. So אמר ליה לבריה amar
lei livrei and now רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
said to his son, בני, beni, my son,
בני אדם הללו, benei adam hallalu, these people, אנשים של צורה הן,
anashim shel tzura hen, they're people of stature, meaning they're you know
meaning a) they're תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim but also means like you
know they know דרך ארץ derech eretz as well, and זיל גבייהו
דליברכוך. zil gabeihu delivarchuach. Go to them, they'll give you a ברכה
beracha like as they're leaving, before they leave town say give me
a ברכה. beracha. Interesting that you had that idea even at that
time. אזל אשכחינהו דקמי קראי אהדדי, azal ashchechinhu dekami kray ahadadi, he
went, he
saw them,
he found them, you know, what do you do when you're traveling?
You talk תורה. Torah. So he saw that they were, they were
dealing with contradictions in פסוקים. pesukim. כתיב ketiv one verse says, פלס
מעגל רגלך וכל דרכיך יכונו, palles magal raglecha vechol derachecha yikonu, weigh
the sort of you know your steps and all of your paths
will be set, you know will be established. וכתיב uchetiiv so you
should make like you should you know you should decide before you
jump into something and what you're going to do. וכתיב uchetiiv but
another verse says, אורח חיים פן תפלס, orech chayyim pen tepalles, the
path of life lest you do a weighing of your steps. Just
seize the moment, don't do this all hesitating and
weighing. So how do you resolve those verses? לא קשיא, la kashya,
it's not difficult. כאן במצווה שאפשר לעשותה על ידי אחרים. kan bemitzvah
she'efshar la'asota al yedei acherim. One is some מצווה mitzvah so they
understand that the verse is not choosing between good and evil, it's
choosing between one מצווה mitzvah and another מצווה. mitzvah. So should you,
if you have to choose between two מצוות, mitzvot, make a חשבון,
cheshbon, wow which is the more important מצווה, mitzvah, which is the
less important מצווה, mitzvah, or should you just say I don't think
about more important less important, if this is a מצווה mitzvah that
presents itself, this is the מצווה mitzvah that I'm going to do?
So it says it depends. Can one of them be done by
somebody else? If something can be done by somebody else and you
don't have to do it, like I don't know, going לשמחת חתן
וכלה. lesimchat chatan vechallah. Okay, so they don't need me, a hundred
other people are going לשמחת חתן וכלה, lesimchat chatan vechallah, not about
me personally. So then you have to make a judgment call. Let
somebody else do that, I'll do the one that other people aren't
doing or that's my personal obligation. That's when you start weighing things.
כאן במצווה שאי אפשר לעשותה על ידי אחרים. kan bemitzvah she'ei efshar
la'asota al yedei acherim. However, if you've got two מצוות mitzvot that
present that you have to deal with and both of them are
your personal obligation or nobody else is around to do it, then
you don't start weighing which is more important which is less important,
you take the one that presents itself to you first. Okay, and
there's other interesting issues about this about you know about עוסק במצווה
פטור מן המצווה, osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah, אין מעבירין על המצוות.
ein maavirin al hamitzvot. I mean עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה osek
bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah is interesting because that's when you already began
doing one you don't stop to do another. That doesn't exactly address
the question about let's say I haven't begun, do I make a
choice which one is better or not? And here the גמרא Gemara
is, now the גמרא Gemara doesn't fully spell out the halachic implications
but it is sort of pushing in that way, which is you
know if you have two obligations that both specifically your responsibility, don't
start making judgment calls bigger and less bigger and so on. You
do the one that, now so which one do I do if
I don't make judgment calls, which one do I do? So רבינו
גרשום Rabbenu Gershom says oh well you do the one that presents
itself to you first. That's not spelled out in the גמרא. Gemara.
And one also doesn't imagine that sometimes you do make choices, like
you know מת מצווה met mitzvah comes before something else, מקרא מגילה
mikra Megillah comes you know takes precedence of תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah.
So it's not always that it's so obvious, yes.
I think it's interesting, if I'm not mistaken, isn't this רבי יהודה
בן גרים? Rabbi Yehuda ben Gerim? Wasn't he the one the ראש
המדברים בכל מקום rosh hamedabrim bechol makom and all
that stuff with the Romans later on?
Yeah that's a good point, and then he ends up saying עדיין
יש כזו בעולם adayin yesh kazo ba'olam and then נתן עיניו בו
ונעשה גל של
עצמות,
natan einav
bo vena'asa gal shel atzamot, right? So in the end didn't they
have a pretty big falling out later?
Right, no you're right, he's in that story in the beginning of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but then but isn't
he the one that stands between the two mountains and gets, no
זה יהודה בן גרים Ze Yehuda ben Gerim I think is the
one that
praises the
Romans, right?
Right, that's a very good
point. Yep, that's a very good
point. Yep, a good point. I'm sure there's some commentary on that.
That's an excellent point. Okay, so הדר יתבי *Hadar Yasvi*, then they
were sitting ובעי בהו *Vekami Ba'ei Lehu* and they dealt with another
contradiction in פסוקים *Pesukim* which is going to have a similar resolution.
כתיב *Kesiv*, one verse says יקרה היא מפנינים *Yekara Hi Mi'peninim*, it
understood to mean Torah is greater than pearls, וכל חפציך לא ישוו
בה *Vechol Chafatzecha Lo Yishvu Bah*, all of your desires cannot equate
to it. הא חפצי שמים ישוו בה *Ha Chafzei Shamayim Yishvu Bah*,
but desires of heaven, מצוות *Mitzvos*, it becomes בין תלמוד תורה ובין
המצווה *Bein Talmud Torah Ve'bein Ha'mitzvah*, מצוות *Mitzvos* should take precedence. וכתיב
*Ukesiv*, but in another verse says כל חפצים לא ישוו בה *Kol
Chafatzim Lo Yishvu Bah*, all all desires, not just your desires, ואפילו
חפצי שמים לא ישוו בה *Ve'afilu Chafzei Shamayim Lo Yishvu Bah*, even
desires of heaven, even מצוות *Mitzvos* don't override תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*.
So which is it? Do מצוות *Mitzvos* override תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*
or not? The answer is כאן במצווה שאפשר לעשותה ע''י אחרים כאן
במצווה שאי אפשר לעשותה ע''י אחרים *Kan Bemitzvah She'efshar La'asotah Al Yedei
Acherim Kan Bemitzvah She'i Efshar La'asotah Al Yedei Acherim*. If somebody else
can do it, like I'm supposed to leave my learning and go
do to every single wedding and every single funeral because that's a
מצווה *Mitzvah*, you know what, other people are available to do that,
I keep on learning. But if it's something that someone else can't
do, I gotta take לולב *Lulav*, I gotta דאוון *Daven*, I gotta
say the שמע *Shema*, then that I have to stop my learning
in order to do that. And that's a much larger discussion about,
you know, whether עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה *Osek Bemitzvah Patur Min
Ha'mitzvah* applies to תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah* and so on. Okay, now
the גמרא *Gemara* continues. אמרו ליה *Amru Leh*, they said to him,
by the way, it's interesting to look at תוספות *Tosafot* because talking
this is the son of רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Rav Shimon Bar
Yochai*. So you look at תוספות *Tosafot*, כאן במצווה שאפשר לעשותה ע''י
אחרים *Kan Bemitzvah She'efshar La'asotah Al Yedei Acherim*, תוספות *Tosafot* says עשיית
מצווה עדיף שהרי מפסיקין אפילו רבי שמעון בן יוחאי *Asiyat Mitzvah Adif
Sheharei Mafsikin Afilu Rabi Shimon Ben Yochai*. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי *Rabi
Shimon Ben Yochai* is like the class, you know, לעשות סוכה ולולב
כדאיתא בירושלמי *La'asot Sukkah Velulav Ked'isa Bi'yerushalmi*. Okay,
so רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rav Shimon Bar Yochai* is like an
example of somebody that's always עוסק בתלמוד תורה *Osek Be'talmud Torah*, but
even he would have to interrupt in order to do like a
מצווה *Mitzvah* of like making a סוכה *Sukkah* and a לולב *Lulav*
etc. But תוספות *Tosafot* says but there are some things that if
you're totally עוסק *Osek* in Torah you don't interrupt for, אבל בהפסקה
דתפילה וקריאת שמע אין מפסיקין רשב''י *Aval Be'hafsakah Detfillah Ukrias Shema Ein
Mafsikin Rashbi*. Why not? That's אי אפשר לעשותה ע''י אחרים *Ee Efshar
La'asotah Al Yedei Acheirim*. ובירושלמי *Uvi'yerushalmi*, so the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* says the
reason is זה שינונו וזה שינונו *Zeh Shinuno Ve'zeh Shinuno*, both of
them are learning Torah. Right, קריאת שמע *Krias Shema* is ושננתם לבניך
*Ve'shinantam Levanecha*. Doesn't exactly explain תפילה *Tfillah*, but at least קריאת שמע
*Krias Shema*, so you don't interrupt תורה *Torah* for קריאת שמע *Krias
Shema*. The whole point of קריאת שמע *Krias Shema* is a form
of תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*, ואין מפסיקין שינון מפני שינון *Ve'ein Mafsikin
Shinun Mifnei Shinun*. Anyway, the interesting thing is that's specifically a discussion
around רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rav Shimon Bar Yochai*. Right, he was
always עוסק בתורה *Osek Ba'torah* and when would he have to interrupt
his תורה *Torah* in order to do מצוות *Mitzvos*. So he's sort
of used as the paradigm and here they're discussing this thing with
the son of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rav Shimon Bar Yochai* is
right over there. So anyway, I'm not saying that they necessarily connected
the dots, but it's just sort of fascinating, you know, that this
similar discourse we find elsewhere in the גמרא *Gemara* specifically around רבי
שמעון בר
יוחאי *Rav Shimon Bar Yochai*. Yes. Where's the exact transition from the
the the ברכה *Bracha* from the חכמים *Chachamim* here?
He didn't get the ברכה *Bracha* yet. He he went to catch
up with them and he interrupted and they found that they were
having this discussion.
And how'd it get to the question of of whether you can
interrupt תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah* or not?
Because that's what they were talking about. הדר יתבי וקמיבעיא *Hadar Yasvi
Vekamibaya*, first line on the עמוד ב *Amud Beis*. First they were
discussing two פסוקים *Pesukim* about weighing your steps and then they were
discussing these two פסוקים *Pesukim*. This was all just he interrupted them
during their discussion.
These are the other פסוקים *Pesukim*.
Yeah, they're talking about what here's one פסוק יקרה היא מפנינים *Pasuk
Yekara Hi Mi'peninim*, another פסוק כל חפצים לא ישוו בה *Pasuk Kol
Chafatzim Lo Yishvu Bah*. So they're having this discussion and then he
he's walking into the room and they're having this discussion. Okay, אמרו
ליה *Amru Leh*, so they said to him, מאי בעית הכא *Mai
Ba'is Hecha*, what are you doing here? אמר Amar להו *Amar Lehu*,
he said to them, דאמר לי אבא זיל לגביהו דליברכוך *De'amar Li
Abba Zil Legabeihu Delivarchuch*, because my father said to me, go to
them that they'll give you a blessing. אמרו ליה *Amru Leh*, they
said to him, יהא רעוא *Yehei Ra'ava*, here's their blessing. It's like
a riddle. יהא רעוא דתזרע ולא תחצד *Yehei Ra'ava Detizra Veloh Thachzad*,
may it be God's will that you will plant and not and
not harvest. Pay off and not pay back? Yes. תעייל ולא תפיק
*Te'ayeil Veloh Sapik*, you'll bring in and not take out, meaning the
assumption here is commerce. You'll like buy goods and not be able
to sell them. תפיק ולא תעייל *Sapik Veloh Te'ayeil*, or you'll export
goods and not be able to import, I mean that's the context,
take out and not bring in. ליחרב ביתך *Lichariv Beisecha*, let your
house be destroyed, וליתוב אושפיזך *Velisiv Ushpizecha*, and let your lodging be
settled. לבלבל פתורך *Levavale Pasurach*, let your table be messed up,
ולא תחזי שתא חדתא velo techzi shata chadta, *Veloh Techzei Shata Chadta*,
and you should not see the new year. Okay, so that was
their blessing. כי אתא לגבי אבוה Ata legabei avuh, *Ki Ata Legabei
Avuhu*, he went back to the father. אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar
Leh*, so he said to the father, לאו מבעיא דברוכי לא ברכן
*Lo Mi'ba'ya Devruchi Lo Birchan*, it's not enough that they didn't bless
me, אבל צעורי צעורן *Aval Tza'urei Tza'uran*, they anguished me, they gave
me a curse, okay, sort of like the reverse. כי אזלא גבי
אבוה, he went back to the father. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
he said to his טאטע, tatta, לא מיבעיא דברכוכי לא ברכון, lo
mibaiya debaruchei lo barchun, it's not enough they didn't bless me, אבל
צעורי צערון, aval tzu'arei tzu'arun, they anguished me, they gave me a
curse. Okay, sort of like the reverse of בלעם, Bilam, right? And
בלק. Balak. You know, I tell you to curse and you blessed
them. I tell you to get a blessing, they gave me a
curse. אמר ליה, amar lei, so the father said, מאי אמרו לך?
mai amru lach? What did they say to you? הכי והכי אמרו
לי, hachi vehachi amru li, so and so, this and this, he
gave told him over. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he was sort
of explaining them to him, הנא כלהו ברכתא נינהו, hanei kulhu birchat
nin'hu, oh no, these are all hidden blessings. How are they blessings?
תזרע ולא תחצד, tizra velo tichtzod, plant and don't harvest. תוליד בנין
ולא ימותו, tolid banin velo yamutu, so seed and planting, right, is
you should have children, but you won't cut them down, they won't
die and, you know, they won't, you won't bury them in your
life. תעול ולא תפוק, teol velo tipok, bring out and don't bring
in, תעול... teol... I mean, bring in and don't bring out. תעול
כלתא, teol kaltha, bring a daughter-in-law into your house because, you know,
when a son gets married, the wife comes to live with the
son. ולא לימותו בנך דליפקו, velo limutu banach delipku, and your sons
shouldn't die that then your daughter-in-law will have to leave your house.
Okay? So you'll bring her in and she won't go out, she'll
stay with you because, you know, everybody will be alive. תפוק ולא
תעול, tipok velo teol, you'll take out and not bring in. So
that's the reverse. תוליד בנתא, tolid banata, you'll have daughters and they'll
go out of your house, they'll marry men. ולא ימותו גבריהו וליהדרו
לוותך, velo yamutu gavrayhu velehaderu levatach, and then their husbands won't die
that they should have to come back to you. Okay. ליחרב ביתך
ולהותיב אושפיזך, licherav beteich ulehotiv ushpizach, let your house be destroyed and
your lodging be settled. דהאי עלמא אושפיזא, dehai alma ushpiza, because this
world is your lodging, it's not your permanent world. Now of course
if you say that, you think what's your permanent world? עולם הבא.
Olam HaBa. So why should that be destroyed? No. You know what
your permanent world is? Talking in very physical sense, your grave. וההוא
עלמא ביתא, vehahu alma beyta, that world, your grave, that's your more
permanent house. Okay? דכתיב, dechtiv, one minute, קרבם בתימו לעולם, kirbam betemo
leolam, you know, their... so their, you know, in their...
how does it translate that? Like their...
in their hearts they'll build houses forever.
Right, thank you. In their house they'll build houses forever. אל תקרי
קרבם, al tikri kirbam, don't read inside of them, אלא קברם, ela
kivram, their graves. Their graves are their eternal house. So your house,
your eternal house, your grave, should be destroyed. Why? תחיית המתים. Techiyat
HaMetim. And therefore what normally is perceived as your temporary lodging, this
world, that'll be settled because you'll be resurrected. And again, we tend
to think about, you know, about the נשמה neshama living afterwards, but
the more fundamental concept of עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, you know, is
when people are resurrected and they live in a future world in
this world. So therefore let your grave, that which is normally seen
as your permanent house, be destroyed, and let your temporary lodging, this
world, be, you know, be settled because you'll live in this world
during, after תחיית המתים. Techiyat HaMetim. All right. That idea of your
grave as your temporary lodging just reminds me of a story, I
think it was, I forget who it was, was it the נודע
ביהודה, Noda BiYehuda, רבי עקיבא איגר. Rabbi Akiva Eiger. Anyway, there's a
story in a town that the person who was like a... made
a lot of money off of everybody in the town because he
lent with, you know, with interest, but he was very, very wealthy,
but, you know, he would lend with interest, made money off of
everybody in the town. So when he died, the חברא קדישא Chevra
Kadisha refused to, like, bury him except for with, you know, an
exorbitant fee for the burial plot, you know, much higher, you know,
they wanted to,
you know, recoup some of the money that the whole town had
given to this person over his lifetime. So they took, so they
took... so the יורשים yorshim took them to a secular court, sued
them.
So they called on the נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda to testify about,
like, how is this, you're charging such a high rate? He says,
listen, you got to understand. He says, we Jews believe in תחיית
המתים. Techiyat HaMetim. So when we charge for a burial plot, we're
really just, it's really just rent. So therefore, you know, that's one
price. This guy was a מלוה בריבית, malve biribit, they don't have
a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. So for him, it was
a permanent sale. All right, anyway, that's the idea of I guess
rabbinic humor. Moving on. Okay, so ליבטב פתורך בבני ובבנתא, libtav petorach
bivney uvivnata,
so let your sort of table be a mess, meaning you'll have
a lot of sons and daughters and, you know, so your house
is a mess. Okay. ולא תחזי שתא חדתא, you should not see
a new year. דלא תמות אנתך ולא תנסב אנתתא
אחריתי, dela tamut intach velo tinsav intata achriti, that your wife shouldn't
die that you shouldn't have to marry another woman because a wife,
you know, when you marry a wife, it says שנה אחת, shana
achat, ושמח את אשתו, vesimach et ishto, שנה אחת. shana achat.
So the new year means the honeymoon year.
It's like somebody said to me when I got married, he says,
I hear you got married, מזל טוב, Mazel Tov, that was a
wonderful thing you did, don't you ever do that again. So just
like this. רב שמעון בר חלפתא Rav Shimon bar Chalafta איפטר מיניה
דרב, iftar minei deRav, so רב שמעון בר חלפתא Rav Shimon bar
Chalafta took his leave of Rav. אמר ליה לבריה, amar lei livreh,
so Rav said to his son, זיל לגביה, zil legabey, go to
רב שמעון בר חלפתא Rav Shimon bar Chalafta דליברכך, delivarchach, he should
give you a blessing. So he went. אמר ליה, Amar lei, יהא
רעוא דלא תבייש ולא תתבייש. yehey ra'ava dela tevayesh velo tityayesh. He
said, may it be God's will that you don't embarrass other people
and as a result... So if you don't, you won't be embarrassed.
It's a little less cryptic, very straightforward. אתא לגבי אבוה, came to
his father. אמר ליה מאי אמר לך? Amar lei mai amar lach?
What did he say to you? אמר ליה מילי דעלמא הוא דאמר
לי. Amar lei milei d'alma hu d'amar li. Yeah, he just gave
me some million dollar talk he gave me. That wasn't a blessing.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him: ברכך ברכתא דמברך
קודשא בריך הוא לישראל. Birchach birchata d'mivarech Kudsha Brich Hu l'Yisrael. What
are you talking about? That's such an amazing blessing. That's the blessing
God gave the Jewish people. ותנא בהו, V'tana behu, and He repeated
it to the Jewish people, He repeated it. דכתיב ואכלתם אכול ושבוע
והללתם וגו' ולא יבושו עמי לעולם. Dich'tiv v'achaltem achol v'savoa v'hillaltem etc.
v'lo yevoshu ami l'olam. I
mean they will never be embarrassed. וידעתם כי בקרב ישראל אני וגו'
ולא יבושו עמי לעולם. Vidatem ki v'kerev Yisrael ani etc. v'lo yevoshu
ami l'olam. So the blessing not to be embarrassed is a very
important blessing and God, you know, and so also the double language
could mean the double aspect of it: don't embarrass others and therefore
you won't be embarrassed. But anyway, do not trivialize the blessing. Quite
fascinating though the idea here that, you know, there seems to have
been this like this like genre of giving blessings in a terse
way or in a type of a riddle or something. Anyway, quite
fascinating. Okay, now the Gemara continues. What?
Another one after the other.
Exactly. Now the Gemara continues. ועושה אשה תכשיטיה. V'osa isha tachshiteha. So
another thing you can do on חול המועד Chol HaMoed is a
woman could do her various makeup, you know, why that should be
a problem is unclear, but okay, maybe you would think that this
involves a lot of effort. Yeah, I guess if whatever. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. אלו הן תכשיטי נשים. Elu hen tachshitei nashim. The following
things are women's makeups that can be done on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. כוחלת, Kochalet, כחל, kachal,
which is basically some type of an eye shadow. פוקסת, Pokeset,
which רש"י Rashi here says the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom here says
it means sort of like, you know, making a part in the
hair type of a combing, could be something else also. ומעבירה שרק
על פניה, U'ma'avira srak al paneha, putting a type of like a
rouge on her cheek. ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amri, and some say, מעברת
שרק על פניה של מטה, ma'averet srak al paneha shel mata, it's
actually some type of a makeup on her genital area.
And whatever, we find elsewhere also that they would do things like
that, that they would, you know, even cut the hair, which we're
going to get to and so on. דביתהו דרב חסדא, D'veitehu d'Rav
Chisda, מיקשטא באנפי כלתה. mikashta b'anpei kaltah.
So the wife of רב חסדא Rav Chisda would put on makeup
in the presence of her daughter-in-law. Now it doesn't seem like it
really matters that it was in the presence of her daughter-in-law other
than to emphasize that she wasn't so young, she had already a
daughter-in-law, okay? That's very funny רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom where he says
באנפי כלתה, b'anpei kaltah, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says שהייתה כל כך
זקנה שהייתה לה כלה. Shehayeta kol kach zkeina shehayeta lah kalah.
She was so old that she had a daughter-in-law. Okay, anyway. What?
Well, I guess, anyway, the point is she, you know, she wasn't
a teenager. יתיב רב הונא בר חיננא קמיה דרב חסדא. Yativ Rav
Huna bar Chinana kamei d'Rav Chisda. So רב הונא בר חיננא Rav
Huna bar Chinana was in front of רב חסדא Rav Chisda ויתיב
וקאמר, v'yativ v'ka'amar, and he was sitting and saying: לא שנו אלא
ילדה. Lo shanu ela yalda. One minute, when we gave an allowance
for makeup, that was for young women, you know, they're very focused
on their looks and so on. אבל זקנה לא, Aval zkeina lo,
an elderly woman, no, it's not allowed. שנא? Shena? Or maybe it's
a question, but it sounds like a statement. אמר ליה, he said
back to him: האלקים, Ha'Elokim, but in God's name, אפילו אמך ואפילו
אמה דאמך, afilu imcha v'afilu ima d'imcha, even your mother and even
your grandmother can put up makeup on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. ואפילו
עומדת על קברה, V'afilu omedet al kivra, even if she was one
step away from the
grave. דאמרי אינשי, D'amri inshi,
because people say: בת שיתין כבת שית, bat shitin k'bat sheis, somebody
who is sixty is like a woman of six, ולקל טבלא רהטא,
u'l'kal tavla rahata,
she'll run after like the sound of the wedding bell, not a
wedding bell, like a bell, a music bell. Meaning just because people
are old doesn't mean that they've given up their zest for life,
you know? Somebody could be sixty years old and there's a wedding
and, you know, not their wedding or whatever it is. Oh my
gosh, שמחה simcha and the joy and exactly. So, you know, so
how, what is it that you decide, oh, somebody's too old to
be caring about those things? Very nice for you to decide that,
you know, the importance of people how they look and how they
appear and their sort of, you know, their sense of joy and
engagement in the world, etc. But the fascinating thing is the sense
that it needed a so it was a good retort but the
fascinating thing is the sense that it needed a particular license, like
what's the problem with makeup? Maybe it's like Michael says that it's
seen as a type of like a writing, צובע, tzoveia, but that
starts pointing us to the idea that מלאכת חול המועד melechet Chol
HaMoed might be more similar to ל"ט מלאכות l'tet melachot and not
so much just about backbreaking hard difficult labor, right? And that's going
to be the ongoing question about what is the character of מלאכת
חול המועד. melechet Chol HaMoed. So the fact that this needed a
היתר, heter, right? That there was a desire to limit it, the
response should just say, what do you want to limit it? There's
no problem with it. No, it sounds like you need a היתר.
heter. It's important for people, therefore we have to allow it. Okay,
so that shows that there's something initially problematic about it which is
quite fascinating. Let's keep on going. טבלא דהילולא? Tavla d'hilula?
No, טבלא tavla is like a bell. ולקל טבלא רהטא, U'l'kal tavla
rahata, she'll run after the sound of...
Yes,
okay.
So רבי יהודה אומר לא תסוד. Rebbi Yehuda omer lo tasid. Rebbi
Yehuda says don't put on plaster to pull off the hair and
to make the skin redder and so on. Okay, sort of like
you know people who pack their face with that mud from the
Dead Sea. תניא, Tanya, it's shown in a ברייתא. braita. רבי יהודה
אומר: Rebbi Yehuda omer: אשה לא תסוד מפני שנוול הוא לה. Isha
lo tasid mipnei shenivul hu lah.
A woman should not put on plaster because it is, you know,
disfiguring, it is disgusting. And therefore she- Well, from there it's not
because it's a מלאכה *melacha*, but it's inappropriate on חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed* to be having this plaster all over you, even if the
end result is nice.
ומודה רבי יהודה
ויוסי בסיד שיכולה לקפל במועד *U-modeh Rabbi Yehuda ve-Yosi basid she-yechola lekappel
bamoed*. Ah, but if it's the type of plaster that you'll pull
off during חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, שתפלתו במועד *she-tefelato bamoed*, you can
put it on. שאף על פי שמיצר היא עכשיו *she-af al pi
she-meitzar hi achshav*, even though it causes some anguish now or disfiguring
now, שמחה היא לאחר זמן *simcha hi leachar zman*, it causes joy
later. So he basically says if it's going to be something that
won't- you won't reap the benefits of it until after חול המועד
*Chol HaMoed* and יום טוב *Yom Tov*, you can't do it. But
if it's something that will be in the bigger context a good
thing over חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, that you can do. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* says, ומי אית ליה לרבי יהודה האי סברא *u-mi
it leh l-Rabbi Yehuda hai sevara*? Does רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* hold
of this idea of this sort of looking at things in a-
you know in a larger context? והתנן *ve-hatnan*, taught in a משנה
*mishna*, רבי יהודה אומר נפרעין מהם מפני שמיצר הוא לו *Rabbi Yehuda
omer nifra'in mehem mipney she-meitzar hu lo*. So this is a discussion
about doing business with non-Jews during their holidays and you're not allowed
to make them pay up their debts, and- because if they have
to pay up their debt, even though you don't want to pay
up your debt, you feel good that you're- it's finally you're free
from debt. So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, you- so you're
not allowed to have them pay up their debts on- on their
holiday. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says you can have them pay up
their debts because at the time of paying up your debts you're-
you're really upset that you had to put out all that money.
So מפני שמיצר הוא לו *mipney she-meitzar hu lo*, so you see
that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* looks only at the very micro. ואמרו
לו *v-amru lo*, and the rabbis said back to him, אף על
פי שמיצר עכשיו *af al pi she-meitzar achshav*, it's true that now
he's anguish, אבל שמח הוא לאחר זמן *aval same'ach hu leachar zman*,
but he's joyous later. So you see this is the debate that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* looks at the micro and the חכמים *Chachamim*
look at the macro. So how could רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* say
you can put on this סיד *sid* on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*
because you're joyous later if he's always just looking at the very-
at the micro? So the גמרא *Gemara* says- שמח הוא לאחר זמן
*same'ach hu leachar zman*. So- so- so the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this, אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman בר יצחק הנח להלכות חול המועד
*Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hanach l-hilchot Chol HaMoed*. No, no, no.
Don't- don't- you can't ask from הלכות *halachot* of חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed*. דכולו מיצר עכשיו ושמח לאחר זמן נינהו *d-kulo meitzar achshav v-same'ach
leachar zman ninhu*. All of them are things that cause some type
of- you know- of- not necessarily anguish but- you know- what's
the word I'm looking for? Anyway, not effort. Anyway, but they cause
some type of a demand from you right now and the joy
is postponed. Why? Just what?
Distress. Yeah, I don't know if distress. Anyway, but you gotta cook,
you gotta bake, you gotta do a lot of things. Like when
you do- when you do work in the kitchen, the pleasure comes
later. Now some people enjoy cooking, but okay. Right,
so stress and so on. So therefore even if normally רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* is very micro, by חול המועד *Chol HaMoed* of course
he's going to look at the bigger picture because of course a
חול המועד *Chol HaMoed* like you might have to be working in
the kitchen in חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. How is this a right-
or even on יום טוב *Yom Tov*? Is this a right thing
to be doing, working in the kitchen on יום טוב *Yom Tov*?
But in the larger context it's שמחה *simcha*. So therefore here he
looks in a larger context even if normally he doesn't. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, רבינא אמר כותי *Ravina amar Kuti*. כותי *Kuti* is
clearly a- a- a-
gloss. What do I call it? You know, a censorship. It should
be like נכרי *Nochri*, a non-Jew, because those are the people who
were paying- you were doing business with them on their
holiday. לעולם מיצר *l-olam meitzar*. If he pays a debt, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*'s position is- the debate of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and
the חכמים *Chachamim* is not the חכמים *Chachamim* say look at the
big picture, the big picture he'll be happy later, and רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says I look only at the small picture and in
the small picture he's upset. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, I
also look at the big picture like I פסק *pasken*'d by the
makeup on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. Except I think in this case
of paying debts the big picture is he's always angry because he
maybe thought he would get out of it, maybe thought he would
never have to pay. So therefore I do look at the big
picture, I just disagree with what the big picture is. Okay. אמר
רב יהודה *Amar Rav Yehuda*. Now says- רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, not
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*. בנות ישראל שהגיעו לפרקן
ולא הגיעו לשנים *Benot Yisrael she-higi'u l-pirkan v-lo higi'u l-shanim*. Now he's
going to talk why people do these type of plasters. So young
girls that they are already seeing pubic hair, that's what הגיעו לפרקן
*higi'u l-pirkan* means, but they're not yet- they're twelve years old. So
they don't like the pubic hair, it feels- you know- it's inappropriate
for their age. עניות סכות אותן בסיד *Aniyot sachot otan b-sid*, so
the poor girls- you know- use plaster as a way of then
pulling out the hair. עשירות סכות אותן בסולת *Ashirot sachot otan b-solet*,
the rich ones use- like a- like a type of a fine
flour mixed paste in order to pull out the hair. בנות מלכים
בשמן המור *Benot melachim b-shemen ha-mor*, and the really super rich ones
use oil of- myrrh oil. שנאמר ששה חדשים בשמן המור *shenemar shisha
chodashim b-shemen ha-mor*, like we see that that's what they did in
the time of אחשורוש *Achashverosh*. מאי שמן המור *mai shemen ha-mor*? What
is this שמן המור *shemen ha-mor*? רב הונא בר חייא אמר סטכת
*Rav Huna bar Chiya amar stachet*. Okay, fine. Olive oil or- or-
myrrh incense, some type of incense oil. רב ירמיה בר אמי אמר
שמן זית שלא הביא שליש *Rav Yirmiya bar Ami amar shemen zayit
she-lo hevi shalish*. It's olive oil that the olives had not ripened
yet a third ripe and therefore somehow it had a certain type
of a pungency that was effective for doing this. תניא תנא קמיה
דרב יהודה *Tanya tana kameh d-Rav Yehuda*, אנפיקינון שמן זית שלא הביא
שליש *anpikinon shemen zayit she-lo hevi shalish*. This אנפיקינון *anpikinon* is olive
oil from olives that has not ripened a third. ולמה סכין אותו
*v-lama sachin oto*? Why do women use this? On their skin שמשיר
את השיער, it causes the hair to fall out if you have
hair in unwanted places, ומעדנת את הבשר u'madenes es habasar
and makes the skin very supple. רב ביבי Rav Bibi had a
daughter, טפלה אבר אבר, tafla eivar eivar, and he one limb at
a time put onto her,
rubbed into her this olive oil in order to make her skin
look supple and to get the hair to come out where it
was unwanted. ושקל בה ארבע מאה זוזי V'shakl bah arba me'ah zuzei
and when it came time to marry her off he got double
value for her; somebody's willing to give 400 זוז zuz to marry
her. Okay, the objectification here of the daughter is clearly a problem.
ההוא כותי Hahu kusi בשיבבותיה, bishvavusei,
there was a certain Samaritan in his neighborhood דהוה ליה ברתא d'haval
barseh he had a daughter. He said, "Oh, what a great idea!
Look how much money you can make off of your daughter if
you do this process." So טפלה בחד זימנא tafla b'chad zimna ומיתת,
umeisas,
but rather he was in too much of a rush, so rather
than do one limb at a time he just did the whole
her, he rubbed this into her whole body at once; so that
was a little bit too powerful, so she died as a result.
אמר he said, קטלה ביבי לברתי, katla Bibi l'varti, "Bibi killed my
daughter." Okay, because I took his example, but of course he wasn't
paying attention that רב ביבי Rav Bibi did it in a more
careful way. אמר רב נחמן בר רב ביבי, Amar Rav Nachman bar
Rav Bibi, so רב נחמן רב ביבי's Rav Bibi son says now
דשתי שיכרא, d'shasi shichra, people who drink mead בעיין בנתייה טפלה. ba'in
bnosei tefela.
So the daughters have to use this because רש"י Rashi says or
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says if you drink mead it makes your
skin rough and puts hair on your knuckles or something, I don't
know, it makes you hairy.
So I don't know if the daughters drink mead or just
daughters of people who drink mead; anyway, they need this type of
treatment. אנן דלא שתינן שיכרא, Anan d'lo shasina shichra, we who don't
drink this mead לא בעיין בנתין טפלה, lo ba'in bnasin tefela, we
don't need to do this. So maybe it's just a good general
advice about don't try to repeat what my father רב ביבי Rav
Bibi did because look what this other person tried to repeat, look
what happened to his daughter. Okay, we continue tomorrow.